Thomas Harrop

I am a post-doctoral researcher with a background in bioinformatics, genetics and molecular biology and an interest in basic and applied research relating to agriculture.

I have advanced programming skills in R, Python and shell scripting. I am experienced working in molecular, plant, animal and medical laboratories and installing, maintaining and using computers running Unix, Linux and MacOS.

Personal information

Date of birth 25 December 1982

Nationalities Australian and British

Languages English (native), German (TELC Level B2) and French

(TELC Level B1)

Education

2006–2012 Doctor of Philosophy, Department of Genetics, the

University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Thesis: <u>The functions of cytochrome P450s in Drosophila</u>. During my Ph.D. I used classical genetics and modern molecular biology, including transgenic manipulation of gene expression and comparative studies of gene function, to investigate the functions of cytochrome

P450 genes in the Drosophila genus.

2002-2005 Bachelor of Science with Honours (first class), the

University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Experience

2014–Present Post-doctoral researcher, UMR DIADE, Institut de

Recherche pour le Développement (IRD), Montpellier,

France.

In my current project I am working on the development of inflorescence architecture in rice, which is related to grain yield potential. We used a precise laser microdissection and RNA sequencing approach to characterise molecular events that occur during the transitions between meristem types in the developing inflorescence. We are now applying these results to study the effects of selection on gene expression during the parallel domestications of African and Asian rice. Whilst working on this project I have expanded my skills in bioinformatic analysis and statistics and gained a knowledge of plant biology and agronomy.

2013-2014 Post-doctoral researcher, Department of Plant
Breeding and Genetics, Max Planck Institute for Plant
Breeding Research, Cologne, Germany.
At the Max Planck Insitute I worked on a project
to compare the transcriptional response of several
different land plants to UV-B exposure, which acts as an
environmental signal. This position provided hands-on
experience with plant biology and a foundation to apply
my programming and bioinformatic skills.

Professional positions

2004–2007 Medical scientist, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital, Heidelberg, Australia.

2001–2004 Laboratory assistant, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital, Heidelberg, Australia.

Teaching

2007–2011 3rd Year Genetics, Department of Genetics, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

2006–2009 High School Biology, Department of Genetics, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

2006–2008 High School Biology, Gene Technology Access Centre, The University High School, Parkville, Australia.

2005–2008 1st Year Genetics, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Students co-supervised

Swarit Jaisal Master of Science, Life Science Informatics, Universität Bonn, Germany.

Axel Verdier Master of Science, Sciences et Technologies de l'Information et de la Communication pour la Santé, Université de Montpellier, France.

Publications

Peer-reviewed journals

- **Harrop, T.W.R.**§, Ud Din, I.§, Gregis, V., Osnato, M., Jouannic, S., Adam, H. and Kater, M. (2016). Gene expression profiling of reproductive meristem types in early rice inflorescences by laser microdissection. The Plant Journal 86, 75–88. doi:10.1111/tpj.13147.
- Harrop, T.W.R.[§], Pearce, S.L.[§], Daborn, P.J. and Batterham, P. (2014). Whole-genome expression analysis in the third instar larval midgut of *Drosophila melanogaster*. G3 (Bethesda) 4, 2197–2205. doi:10.1534/g3.114.013870.
- Harrop, T.W.R., Sztal, T., Lumb, C., Good, R.T., Daborn, P.J., Batterham, P. and Chung, H. (2014). Evolutionary changes in gene expression, coding sequence and copy-number at the *Cyp6g1* locus contribute to resistance to multiple insecticides in Drosophila. Plos One 9, e84879. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0084879.
- Daborn, P.J., Lumb, C., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Blasetti, A., Pasricha, S., Morin, S., Mitchell, S.N., Donnelly, M.J., Müller, P. and Batterham, P., (2012). Using *Drosophila melanogaster* to validate metabolism-based insecticide resistance from insect pests. Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 42, 918–924. doi:10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.09.003.

Selected scientific presentations

- Harrop, T.W.R. Gene expression during *O. sativa* panicle development. Invited seminar, 19 November 2015, LMI RICE, Hanoi, Vietnam.
- Harrop, T.W.R., Gregis, V., Ud Din, I., Kater, M., Jouannic, S. and Adam, H. *Molecular mechanisms* underlying the phenotypic convergence of inflorescence architecture in domesticated rice species. Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution annual meeting, 2015, Vienna, Austria
- **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Ud Din, I., Gregis, V., Osnato, M., Jouannic, S., Adam, H. and Kater, M. *Transcriptomic analysis of early developmental stages of the rice panicle*. Workshop in Molecular Mechanisms Controlling Flowering, 2015, Aiguablava, Spain.
- **Harrop**, **T.W.R.**, Batterham, P. and Daborn, P.J. RNA interference of the Cytochrome P450 redox partners Cpr and dare uncovers novel P450 functions in Drosophila melanogaster. The 50th Annual Drosophila Research Conference, 2009, Chicago, USA.

[§] Equal contribution

Other information

Research interests Plant and insect research related to **agronomy**, tools

and techniques in bioinformatics and evolutionary and

comparative biology.

Technical experience Aside from daily use of R, Python and bash scripts, I

also use Markdown regularly and have experience with Perl, LaTeX, html and css. I use git and GitHub for version control and strive to follow the principles of reproducible research when coding. I have used several different workload managers for cluster computing including SGE and and LSF, and I maintain an installation

of SLURM on my personal workstation.

I have experience in molecular biology techniques such as quantitative real-time PCR, cloning, nucleic acid extraction and cDNA library preparation, as well as classical genetic approaches with live organisms, such as transformation, crosses, microdissection and bioassays.

About me Outside work I have a range of interests including

building and riding bicycles, social football and basketball, cooking, programming and technology.

Awards 2006–2009, Australian Postgraduate Award

twharrop@gmail.com · GitHub · stackoverflow
Castelnau-le-Lez, Hérault, FRANCE